"The Side Effects of Quinine (Tonic Water)
to Boost GLP-1"
In my last video,
I talked about how
the quinine in a third
of a liter of tonic water
can suppress appetite
and cause people to lose weight.
But there are "risks
for the consumption of quinine."
Quinine is a drug
and may in fact be among
the most common causes
of severe
drug-induced disorders.
Just the levels of quinine
found in tonic water
may cause potentially fatal
immunologically-mediated
hypersensitivity reactions,
basically
like allergic reactions,
where it interacts
with antibodies
to trigger autoimmune reactions
that can cause chills, fever,
a drop in blood pressure,
painful bluish discoloration
of the hands and feet,
and clotting
within your blood vessels.
It can also chew up
your red blood cells,
leading to anemia.
Chew up your platelets, leading
to bleeding and bruising.
And chew up
your white blood cells,
leading to immune dysfunction.
As well as
acute kidney injury,
the dissolution of your muscles,
liver toxicity, heart damage,
respiratory failure,
low blood sugars, blindness,
and toxic epidermal necrolysis,
which can manifest
as genital blistering,
sloughed penile erosion,
or an eroded scrotum.
Even minute exposure to quinine
in common beverages
can cause
severe adverse reactions
involving multiple
organ systems.
So, the "moral of the story"
is that a relaxing gin and tonic
may be the cause
of life-threatening disease.
Now, these are rare,
idiosyncratic reactions.
Just because peanuts
can be life-threatening
to someone with a peanut allergy
doesn’t mean everybody
needs to avoid peanuts.
But there are
non-hypersensitivity
adverse effects, too.
For example, when quinine
isn’t eroding scrotums,
it may still be shrinking them.
Researchers found quinine
so damaging
to the testicles of rats
that they suggested
that quinine should be explored
as male contraceptive.
Quinine is an extremely toxic
agent in overdose,
with vision loss
as a common outcome.
The reason people may have
quinine pills around their house
is that some people take them
for nocturnal leg cramps.
The U.S. Food and Drug
Administration concluded
that this was not safe;
so, it banned quinine’s use
for this purpose in both
over-the-counter preparations
and even in prescriptions,
after receiving
hundreds of reports
of serious adverse events
associated with quinine use,
including 93 deaths.
It’s still available
with a prescription
as a malaria drug, though,
which doctors were
prescribing for leg cramps,
skirting FDA recommendations,
but given its rare but serious
allergic-type reactions,
and risk of OD’ing
on quinine pills,
that’s probably not a good idea.
Thankfully,
following warnings by the FDA,
the use of quinine
for treatment of muscle cramps
has dramatically declined.
Of course, even though
the FDA banned it
from one aisle
of the drug store,
it still may be available
in another,
in the form of tonic water.
Yeah, but can
the lower levels of the drug
found in drinks
still cause problems?
Yes, an overdose
can leave you blind,
affecting not only the retina
in the back of your eye
but the iris in the front,
leading to oval pupils.
How bizarre is that?
Okay, okay,
but what if you don’t overdose?
Can quinine
still affect your vision?
Following the identification
by the Armed Forces
Institute of Pathology
of quinine in autopsy specimens
from military pilot fatalities,
researchers had volunteers
drink tonic water
for two weeks and were indeed
able to show some abnormalities.
Even transient blurring
of vision
can be disastrous if experienced
by anyone operating
heavy machinery at high speeds.
So, given the concern
that tonic water consumption
may have contributed
to aviation accidents,
the use of tonic water by pilots
is actually forbidden
three days before flying.
I didn’t know that.
So, how much is too much?
There was a case reported
of a 46-year-old man
with increasing
visual deterioration
and difficulty with
night driving over three months,
during which
he had been drinking
a gallon of tonic water a day.
Okay, so, a gallon
may be too much.
This person was drinking
a liter of tonic water
prior to the onset of his
"Quinine water-triggered
heart arrhythmia."
His doctors suggest the public
is simply unaware of the risks
associated with excessive
consumption of tonic water,
but how many people are drinking
almost a quart a day?
The "no-untoward-effect"
level in humans
has been estimated to be
52.5 mg of quinine a day,
which is about a two and a half
cups (590 ml) of tonic water.
Based on ototoxicity,
damage to our hearing,
maybe we shouldn’t
drink much more
than two cups (470 ml) a day,
but these levels are based on
trying to extrapolate
from animal models.
Since quinine was so commonly
prescribed to treat leg cramps,
can’t we just look at large
populations of people
and see if anything
bad happened?
Yes, indeed, we can,
and those prescribed quinine
had a 27 percent increased risk
of acute kidney injury,
which is not as bad as death:
"Association Between
Long-term Quinine Exposure
and All-Cause Mortality."
Following 175,000 people
for about six years,
researchers found
that those who were taking
about 200 mg of quinine a day
had a 25 percent
greater risk of dying.
Those on around 300 mg
had an 83 percent
greater risk of dying,
and those on 400 mg or more
appeared to double
their risk for death.
So, I would recommend
staying away from quinine.
Although the FDA has determined
that carbonated beverages
may safely contain up to 83 mg
of quinine per liter,
bottles of bubbly drinks usually
don’t say how much is in them,
and some popular brands
don’t even list it
as an ingredient at all.
How do you know if your drink
has quinine or not?
Hold it up to a black light,
and if it lights up
with an iridescent blue glow,
well, quinine
is the secret ingredient
for making
fluorescent Jell-O shots.